Finding Aid for Gordon Alexander Sutherland Papers, 1938-1957
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gordon Alexander Sutherland papers 1938-1957
Sutherland, Gordon Alexander, 1906-1957.
3.5 linear feet
8714 Aa 2
Professor of music at the University of Michigan; include correspondence, subject files, organizational files, and other materials relating to his professional career and University of Michigan teaching and other responsibilities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Gordon A. Sutherland (donor no. 6284 ) and came to the library in 1979.
The collection is open to research.
Gordon Alexander Sutherland was born in Sacramento, California, on February 4, 1906. He took his early musical training at the American Conservatory in Chicago, receiving there the degrees of Bachelor of Music and Master of Music. He taught at the American Conservatory, at Grinnell College, and, returning to his home state, for eight years at Pomona College.
He continued his higher education in musicology at Harvard University, earning his MA and then in 1942, his Ph.D. During his studies he was honored by a Naumberg Fellowship, a John K. Paine Traveling Fellowship, and a Bawdoin Essay Prize. His dissertation dealt with an important phase in the history of instrumental music, "The Ricercare from Willaert to Frescobaldi."
During World War II, he served as personnel director of the Radio Research Laboratory established by the U.S. Government Office of Scientific Research and Development at Harvard University. From 1946 on, he was Dean of the School of Fine Arts, Head of the Department of Music, and Professor of Music at Miami University in Oxford, Ohio. He also conducted the Miami University Symphony Orchestra.
Gordon Sutherland came to the University of Michigan first as a lecturing guest in December, 1951. He was appointed Lecturer the following year and Professor of Music in February, 1953. He was specifically charged with the coordination of graduate studies in music and was appointed to the chairmanship of the advisory and administrative committees on graduate studies established at that time. As liaison officer, he tightened the relations between the School of Music and the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies. During his tenure as Coordinator, he worked toward the establishment of programs leading to the degree Doctor of Musical Arts. The degree was formally established by the Board of Regents of the University of Michigan in November, 1953.
Gordon Sutherland was also instrumental in the acquisition of the Stellfeld Music Library by the University of Michigan. His interest in books led to his appointment to the Library Council of the University in February, 1954. Active in other university committees, Sutherland received appointment to the Fine Arts Divisional Research Committee of the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies.
Gordon Sutherland died in 1957.
The Sutherland collection include correspondence, subject files, organizational files, and other materials relating to his professional career and University of Michigan teaching and other responsibilities. The papers have been divided into the following series: Biographical/Personal; Correspondence; Lecture Notes; Manuscripts of writings and speeches; Professional Organizations; University of Michigan Committee Work; University of Michigan School of Music; and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Stellfeld collection.; University of Michigan. Committee on Responsibilities of Faculty to Society.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Library Council.; University of Michigan. Music Library.; University of Michigan. School of Music.; University of Michigan. Senate.
- Biographical/Personal
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Memorial tributes 1957 (Box 1)
  - Diary (brief) of wartime service as personnel director of the Radio Research Laboratory 1942 (Box 1)
    (volume also used for minutes of the McGuffey P.T.A., 1952-1953)
- Correspondence
  - 1940 (Box 1)
  - 1941 (Box 1)
  - 1942 (Box 1)
  - 1943 (Box 1)
  - 1944 (Box 1)
  - 1945 (Box 1)
  - 1946, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1947 (Box 1)
  - 1948 (Box 1)
  - 1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950 (Box 1)
  - 1951 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1952 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1952 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1953 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1953 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1954 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1954 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1955 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1955 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1955 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1956 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1956 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1957 (Box 1)
  - April-December 1957 (Box 1)
  - Letters of condolence to Mrs. Sutherland 1957 (Box 1)
- Lecture notes
  - Music history undated (Box 2)
  - Music theory undated (Box 2)
  - Bach Cantatas (Box 2)
  - Music 22-Survey of Music to 1620 undated (Box 2)
  - Music 200-Harpsichord literature undated (Box 2)
  - Music 211-History of Instrumental music Summer 1954 (Box 2)
  - Music 248 1953 (Box 2)
  - Musicology 211 undated, 1954-1955 (Box 2)
  - Musicology 227 1952-1955, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Musicology 247-248 1952-1954 (Box 2)
  - Music education 111-112 1955-1956 (Box 2)
  - Analysis of fugue undated (Box 2)
  - Analysis of well-tempered Clavier undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea undated (Box 2)
  - U-M Extension Service lectures
    - "Music in the Community of Arts'' 1953 (Box 2)
    - ''What to Listen for in Music" 1954 (Box 2)
- Manuscripts of writings and speeches
  - Undated
    - "Bach-Recitative and Arioso" (Box 2)
    - "Canonic and imitative writing in the works of Okeghem" (Box 2)
    - "On certain Germanic elements in western music'' (Box 2)
    - "Deutschland uber alles'' (Box 2)
    - "Extra-musical elements in the chorale preludes of J. S. Bach'' (Box 2)
    - "Structure of Lassus 4 voiced motets" (Box 2)
    - "Musical criticisms, ca. 1600-1750" (Box 2)
    - "The ricercari of Jacques Buus" (Box 2)
    - "Some questions about Okeghem" (Box 2)
      (including copy read at A.M.S. Chapter meeting)
    - "The two fugue types in Bach's well-tempered clavier" (Box 2)
  - 1938
    - "A Study of the Use of Dissonance from the Parisian through the Burgundian School'' (Box 2)
  - 1939
    - "The Structure of Palestrina's Five-voiced Motets of 1585" (Box 2)
    - "The Structure of the Rapid Movements in Bach's Sonatas for Two and Three Instruments'' (Box 2)
  - circa 1941
    - "The Schweitzerian Heresy'' (Box 2)
  - 1954
    - "Place of Applied Music in the Liberal Arts College Curriculum'' (Box 2)
  - 1957
    - "Schweitzer on the 'Absolute Music' of J.S. Bach'' (Box 2)
  - Addresses 1950 (Box 2)
- Professional Organizations
  - American Musicological Society
    - Constitution and organization 1956 (Box 2)
    - Minutes 1955 (Box 2)
    - Meeting schedules and exhibits 1953-1954 (Box 2)
    - Newsletter 1956 (Box 2)
    - Program committee 1953-1956 (Box 2)
    - Liaison committee 1954-1955 (Box 2)
    - Committee on graduate studies 1954 (Box 2)
    - Accrediting committee 1955 (Box 2)
  - Music Teachers National Association
    - Correspondence 1952-1955 (Box 3)
    - Program committee 1953-1955 (Box 3)
  - National Association of Schools of Music
    - Correspondence 1951-1955 (Box 3)
    - Membership list 1951 (Box 3)
    - Library committee 1952-1955 (Box 3)
  - Society for Music in the Liberal Arts College
    - Correspondence 1952-1957, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Constitution undated, 1955 (Box 3)
    - Newsletters 1952-1956 (Box 3)
    - Minutes, memos, and reports 1952-1955 (Box 3)
    - Membership lists 1952-1956 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous manuscript articles undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
- University of Michigan Committee Work
  - Library Council
    - Memorandum 1954-1956 (Box 3)
    - Minutes 1953-1956 (Box 3)
    - Annual reports 1953-1956 (Box 3)
    - Annual budget 1955-1957 (Box 3)
    - Report regarding need for space 1954 (Box 3)
    - Midwest library center 1954-1955 (Box 3)
  - Joint committee on training of teachers
    - Correspondence 1953-1956 (Box 3)
    - Minutes 1953-1954, 1956 (Box 3)
    - Reports and proposals undated, 1953-1956 (Box 3)
    - Report on general education: state of Michigan 1957 (Box 3)
  - Rackham research committee, fine arts
    - Correspondence 1954-1956 (Box 3)
    - Grant applications and reports 1954-1957 (Box 3)
  - University Senate
    - Minutes 1954-1956 (Box 3)
    - Reports and recommendations undated, 1954 (Box 3)
    - Reports and recommendations 1955-1956 (Box 3)
    - Miscellanea (Box 3)
  - Senate advisory committee
    - Correspondence 1955 (Box 3)
    - Papers 1957 (Box 3)
  - Committee on responsibilities of faculty to society
    - Correspondence 1954-1955 (Box 3)
    - Articles undated (Box 3)
    - Article: The Fifth Amendment, by Dean Erwin N. Griswold, 1955 (Box 3)
    - Newspaper clippings, concerning the firing of two faculty members 1954, 1955 (Box 3)
- University of Michigan School of Music
  - Correspondence 1953-1955 (Box 3)
  - Faculty meeting minutes 1954-1956 (Box 3)
  - Faculty directory 1953-1955 (Box 3)
  - Administrative committee on graduate studies in music
    - Correspondence 1953-1954 (Box 3)
    - Minutes 1953-1955 (Box 3)
    - Reports 1954 (Box 3)
  - Doctor of Musical Arts
    - Correspondence 1954-1955 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, between Paul Henry Lang and Howard Hanson 1953-1954 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, with Leigh Gerdine 1954 (Box 3)
    - Newspaper clippings 1953 (Box 3)
    - Degree outline 1953 (Box 3)
  - Music education curriculum for Ph.D. undated (Box 3)
  - Advisory committee
    - Correspondence 1955 (Box 3)
    - Minutes 1953-1955 (Box 3)
  - Review committee
    - Reports and recommendations, to advisory committee 1955 (Box 3)
    - Statistics for annual reports 1954 (Box 3)
    - Prelim evaluation 1955 (Box 3)
  - Music library
    - Correspondence 1953-1955 (Box 3)
    - Bibliography 1955 (Box 3)
    - Annual report 1952-1954 (Box 3)
    - Stellfeld collection
      - Correspondence 1954 (Box 3)
      - Cables 1954 (Box 3)
      - Partial inventory 1954 (Box 3)
      - Article by Bernard E. Wilson undated (Box 3)
      - Article, "The University of Michigan's purchase of the Stellfeld music library'' 1954 (Box 3)
    - Einstein Collection (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  - Notes, brochures, Miami University miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Manuscripts of musical composition exercises of Sutherland and others, 3 folders (Box 4)